<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Data Project on &lt;span class=&#34;top&#34;&gt;Lucas&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;bottom&#34;&gt;van Dijk&lt;/span&gt;</title>
    <link>https://lucasvandijk.nl/categories/data-project/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Data Project on &lt;span class=&#34;top&#34;&gt;Lucas&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;bottom&#34;&gt;van Dijk&lt;/span&gt;</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018 Lucas van Dijk</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://lucasvandijk.nl/categories/data-project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Visualising the height of the Netherlands</title>
      <link>https://lucasvandijk.nl/2018/02/visualising-the-height-of-the-netherlands/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lucasvandijk.nl/2018/02/visualising-the-height-of-the-netherlands/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On this date 65 years ago, February 1st 1953, the Netherlands experienced its
greatest flood till date, the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/North_Sea_flood_of_1953&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;North Sea Flood of 1953&lt;/a&gt;. This
is still one of the biggest disasters the Netherlands has ever experienced,
with thousands of casualties and lots of people who lost their homes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Netherlands earns its name from the fact that large parts of the country
lie below sea level. To make sure our country doesn&amp;rsquo;t flood, we have built lots
of barriers, dams and dykes to keep the water out, and we want to prevent
anything like the flood of 1953 from happening ever again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the beginning of this year, several of these barriers and dams were put to
the test when a heavy storm reached the Netherlands which resulted in very high
water levels. Our five biggest dams and barriers needed to be closed at the
same time, a first since their construction. We can ask ourselves the question
whether this will happen more often now that sea levels are rising due to
global warming &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:sealevel&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:sealevel&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. A higher base line sea level increases the chance
for even higher water levels when it storms. To get an idea what areas would be
affected the most by a possible flood, we have created a visualisation project
that shows the height of the Netherlands in comparison to the sea level.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>